它会自动跟随
It's gonna automatically follow.
完美
Perfect.
你现在在左上方
Apparently you live in the top right, top left.
我们开始吧
We'll just go.
你好黑客们
Hello hackers.
欢迎来到CSE 598高级漏洞研究课程
Welcome to CSE 598 Advanced Vulnerability Research.
实际上是漏洞应用研究
It's actually Applied Vulnerability Research.
打在幻灯片上的
Type on the slide.
好的，开了个好头
All right, we're off to a good start.
这个版本的漏洞应用研究聚焦在XNU上
This iteration of AVR is focusing on XNU.
它是苹果各种操作系统的基础
It's the basically base of all of Apple's various operating systems.
我们会有很多有趣的时光
We're gonna have a lot of fun stuff, fun times
在macOS基础上做一些疯狂的事情
doing some crazy stuff in kind of macOS underpinning land.
首先
First things first.
我是Adam Doupe
I'm Adam Doupe.
我是亚利桑那州立大学网络安全专业的副教授
I am an Associate Professor here at ASU in Cyber Security.
简单介绍一下
Just a quick introduction.
你可能从其他教授那里听过
You might have heard from other upstart professors here
他们觉得自己比亚当·杜普还酷
that they think they're cooler than Adam Doupe.
没人比亚当·杜普更酷了
No one is cooler than Adam Doupe.
我想，尤其是对Twitch上的观众，说这句话
I want to say that right now especially for the people watching on Twitch.
作为亚当·杜佩
As Adam Doupe
我作为shellphish的一员，参加过世界黑客锦标赛
I've competed on Team shellphish in the World Championships of Hacking
然后又共同创立了Order of the Overflow
and then went on to co-found the Order of the Overflow.
我和我的新朋友Zardus(Yan)一起举办了世界黑客锦标赛
We ran the World Championship of Hacking with a new friend of mine, Zardus.
我创建了CTFRadi.ooo
I've created the CTFRadi.ooo
我不知道你们是否喜欢播客
I don't know if you guys are into podcasts
但我强烈推荐CTFRadi.ooo
but I highly recommend CTFRadi.ooo
这是个很酷的播客
It's a really cool podcast.
我是pwn学院的核心人物之一
I am one of the core people behind pwn College
最近成为了
and recently became
Defcon学院二进制开发的主任
the Dean of Binary Exploitation of something called Defcon Academy.
告诉你所有的朋友，亚当·杜普，亚利桑那州立大学最好的网络安全教授。
Tell all your friends, Adam Doupe, best Cyber Security professor at ASU.
好了，明白了吗
Alright, got that out of the way?
有谁是亚当·杜佩的忠实粉丝了吗?
Who here a big fan of Adam Doupe?
好的
Yeah, alright.
Twitch上有什么动静吗
You have Twitch action?
大家都是Adam Doupe的粉丝了吗
People are fans of Adam Doupe?
好的，我们可以等一等一些twitch的用户
Alright, we can wait a little bit for some Twitch love.
是的，好的，很好。
Yes, alright, good.
我们等到了twitch里的粉丝，好的，完美
We got Twitch love. Alright, perfect.
亚当·杜普，亚利桑那州立大学最棒最酷的网络安全教授。
Adam Doupe, best and coolest Cyber Security professor at ASU.
好的，继续。
Alright, anyways, moving on.
这门课是什么?
What is this course?
我已经提前说了，cs598。
Well, I just said basically already, going off the rails, CSE 598.
这是一门高级漏洞应用研究课程
This is a graduate level course on applied and advanced vulnerability research techniques.
如果可以，我会把它命名为AAVR。
If I could, I would have named it AAVR.
镜头跟丢我了
the camera lost me.
对镜头来说太酷了
Alright, too cool for the camera.
好了，再说一遍
Alright, so, again
上个迭代版本的漏洞应用研究中
the last iteration of applied vulnerability research.
我们专注于寻找真实程序中的bug
We went in and focused on finding bugs in real programs.
我们找到并利用了大量真实程序中的漏洞
We had a large amount of real programs that we were finding and exploiting bugs in.
在这个版本中，我们继续扩展
This iteration, we're ramping things up to 11.
我们只看支撑你的笔记本电脑的真实软件
The only thing we're going to be looking at is real software underpinning your laptop.
等等，你的不是MacBook。
Wait, that's not a MacBook.
好吧，这里谁有苹果产品?
Alright, who here runs Apple products in any capacity?
好吧，大概有四个人。
Alright, like four people in the class.
好的,完美
Okay, perfect.
我们俩，我们试过Linux
Yeah, well, us two, you see, we tried Linux.
Adam Doupe是Linux的忠实粉丝
Adam Doupe a big fan of Linux.
不幸的是，没成功
Unfortunately, it didn't work.
总之，这门课的目标是。
So anyways, alright, so, goal of this course.
好了，有谁熟悉pwn学院的?
Alright, who here is familiar with pwn College?
很好，pwn学院，很酷的平台。
Excellent, okay, so, pwn College, cool platform.
它能带你从菜鸟到几乎老鸟
It takes you from zero to almost hero, right?
一开始你不需要很多基础知识
You start out not necessarily knowing anything
等你学完这个平台的课
and by the time that you've gone through the platform,
你会知道很多网络安全技能的组成部分
you know a lot of building blocks of these cyber security skills.
你会知道如何利用内核
You know how to exploit a kernel.
知道ROP的原理
You know how ROP works.
知道如何逆向软件
You know how to reverse engineer software.
知道如何发现不同种类的bug，等等
You know how to spot different types of bugs, etc., etc., etc.
但要将这些用在一个实际系统上，仍是需要迈出的一大步
But putting that all together on a real system is still a big step.
这就是这门课的目标
That's what this class is for.
这门课是为了弥补pwn学院其他课程的不足
This class is here to bridge the gap from the rest of the pwn College material
让你们能在真实的软件中找到真实的bug
into basically stepping into a real role of finding real bugs in real software.
然后对它们进行推理，利用它们，
And then reasoning about them, exploiting them,
考虑它们的影响，并如何修复它们等等
reasoning about the effects and what might be done to fix them and so on.
好吧
Alright
运气好的话，一切顺利
with any luck, all of this will work out great
你们会继续进步
and you will all go forth
找到很多XNU和其它平台的bug，并促使其被修复
and find and cause to be fixed many, many bugs in XNU and other complex targets
因为经过在最重要的目标之一
because now after having done having found bugs and analyzed and reasoned about
iOS和MacOS的内核，和其它有趣的东西上
one of the most important targets out there
寻找、分析bug后
the kernel underpinning iOS and Mac OS and all this fun stuff,
你会觉得，其它的东西
you'll be like whatever, everything else.
比如，Linux，就是小孩子的把戏
You know, Linux, child's play.
也许你能够把我那该死的笔记本修好
Maybe you can fix whatever the fuck happened to my stupid laptop.
对不起，刚才不是亚当·杜普在讲话
Sorry, that wasn't Adam Doupe speaking.
有点现出了Yan的原形
That was a bit of  Yan coming out.
那这门课将如何进行呢?
Alright, so how will the class work?
我们每周开一次会
You notice we have one weekly meeting.
那将是很长的会
That is a long meeting.
今天不会很长
Today is not going to be long.
首先，我一会儿会离开
For one, I have to run
Rob会接手教学的部分
and Rob has been kind enough to take on the load of teaching,
完成一个ARM的极速速成课
the very first refresher/hyperfast crash course into ARM.
我们马上会讲到
We'll get to that soon.
在每周的会议上
In the weekly meetings
我们会尽我们所能
we're going to do whatever we need to do.
有时我们会做讲座
Sometimes we'll do lectures.
有时我们会讨论XNU子系统，
Sometimes we'll have discussions about XNU subsystems,
关于它的漏洞研究
about parts of the vulnerability research process, right?
作为亚利桑那州立大学最酷的教授，亚当·杜佩，
As the coolest professor at ASU, Adam Doupe, I, Adam Doupe
我花了一年的假
has spent a whole sabbatical year
寻找XNU中的bug
finding bugs in XNU.
这是你们可以做的
This is an actual thing you can do.
你们可以靠这个谋生
You can make a living doing this.
我们会讨论这个过程中的经验和教训
And we'll discuss that experience, lessons learned there.
我们会读代码
We'll read code.
会深入研究实际的内核代码
We'll plunk through actual kernel codes
尝试理解bug，并深入研究它们等等
to try to understand bugs and dig into them and so on.
酷
Awesome.
好的
Okay
我们也会在pwn学院上布置作业任务
we'll also have a bunch of assignments on pwn College.
有多少人在pwn学院做过作业?
How many have done assignments on pwn College?
好吧
Okay
有人没用过pwn学院吗?
has anyone not used pwn College?
好吧
Okay
我们会
we will.
我快速演示一下pwn学院的使用
Let me just show you real quick pwn College.
我看看时间用的怎么样
Let's see how we're doing on time.
很充裕
Doing great.
好的，pwn学院已经开了
Yes, okay, pwn College is already up.
访问https://pwn.college
Boom, go to https://pwn.college.
有很多很酷的网络安全材料
A lot of really cool cybersecurity material.
我们的这个课程在这里
All of our class is going to live in here
在Courses部分
in the courses section
它是先进前沿的课程
and in the very most advanced course
因为ASU最酷的网络安全教授
because the coolest cybersecurity professor at ASU
教最先进的课
teaches the most advanced course
除了Rob的课
except for Rob's course
但没关系
but it's fine.
好的，那么
All right, so
现在发布了一个作业任务
right now there's one assignment live.
就是这个arm的介绍
It's the introduction to ARM.
它已经上线了
So it's already live.
我不知道它什么时候到期，如果
I don't know when it to due, actually, if you can
它到期的时候，你会知道的
You can find out when it's due.
你点进去
You click in.
能看到它会在7天7小时17分钟后到期
You can see it's due in seven days, seven hours, and 17 minutes.
有很多时间
That's a lot.
很多吗?
That's a lot?
他们将会在晚上8点看到它
They'll see it at 8 p.m.
等等,什么?
Wait, what?
哦，我的错。
Oh, my bad.
你会在晚上8点发布
This is how you're going to launch at 8 p.m.
我们能看到，是因为登录的管理员账号
There's an administrator logged in so we can see it.
好的
It's fine.
不管怎样
Anyways
今晚，第一份作业将在pwn学院发布
first assignment launch is tonight on pwn College.
是的，现在是隐藏的
Yeah, here it's hidden.
你能看到是因为现在是dojo（道场）的管理员
You can see this because you're the Dojo's administrator.
好，你们现在看不到
Great, but you shouldn't be able to see the module itself.
没关系。
It doesn't matter.
去这个地方
Go to this thing.
太棒了。
It's great.
好了，有一件非常重要的事
All right, one extremely important thing
对那三个
extremely important for the three people that
没参与过pwn学院课程的人，十分重要
haven't done course on pwn College.
进入这里
Go in here.
点击这个课程相关的东西
You click on this course thing.
点击设置
You click on Setup.
好的教学大纲中，应该也有这个链接
All right, there should also be a link from the syllabus.
确保你在这里有五个绿色的勾。
Make sure that you have five green check marks here.
这里Rob只有一个
This, Rob only has one.
你这门课会挂
You will fail this course.
如果你没有五个绿色的勾
You don't have five green check marks.
你这门课会不及格
You will fail the course.
这门课最难的就是拿到这五个绿色勾
The hardest thing about this course is getting these five green check marks.
要得到五个绿色的勾
To get the five green check marks
你必须创建一个pwn学院账户
you have to create a pwn College account.
你必须创建一个Discord账号
You have to create a Discord.
你必须将pwn学院和Discord帐户关联起来。
You have to link the pwn College and Discord account.
你必须加入这个
You have to join the thing.
录入你的学生id
you know puts your student ID.
它无所不能。
It does everything.
好了，你的成绩就在Grades下面。
All right, your grades are going to be available right here under Grades.
不幸的是，Rob现在这门课不及格。
Unfortunately, Rob's failing the course right now.
这些可能会自动同步到Canvas
These will be auto-synced to Canvas maybe.
不会？
No?
这门课有Canvas吗?
Is there Canvas for this course?
好吧，去他的Canvas。
Okay, fuck Canvas.
这不是亚当说的
Again, that wasn't Adam saying that.
这不会同步到Canvas
This will not be synced to Canvas.
让我们忘掉Canvas吧
Let's forget about Canvas.
好
Good.
这是你的成绩。
So that's your grade.
那么基本上就可以开始了
Then you're basically good to go.
五个检查标记
Five check marks.
非常重要
Very important.
别看那张照片
Don't look at that picture.
它过时了
It's outdated.
好吧
Okay.
还有什么？
What else?
我想我们不会占用大家的时间。
I guess we won't spend everyone's time.
我就展示一下如何启动。
I'll just show how to launch.
展示去哪里学习pwn学院的使用方法
I'll show where to go to learn how to use pwn College.
回到pwn学院的主页
If you go to the homepage of pwn College
去这里，Getting Started。
and you go here, Getting Started.
嘿,家伙。
Hey, guys.
请不要迟到。
Please don't come in late.
我，亚当·杜普，对这种事很生气。
I, Adam Doupe, get upset when this happens.
不，我只是在开玩笑。
No, I'm just kidding.
亚当·杜普并不介意。
Adam Doupe does not mind.
好的
Okay.
你可以点击“Getting Started”
You can click Getting Started
通过这个来学习如何使用道场dojo。
and go through this to learn how to use the dojo.
好吧?
All right?
现在有20个人正在学习如何使用道场。
There's 20 people learning how to use the dojo right this moment.
只是一些简单的挑战题目。
Just a couple of nice and easy challenges.
你将经历，假设你想学习如何使用图形桌面。
You will go through, let's say you want to learn how to use the GUI desktop.
你点击开始。
You hit Start.
它开始加载
It loads.
会在后台启动一个容器
Starting up a container in the background.
现在是开学的第一周
Right now, it's the first week of school.
有很多人。
There's a lot of people.
我们说
And we say
“好的，我们用GUI桌面连接到容器。”
"Okay, we're going to connect to our container using the GUI desktop."
还在加载
It loads more.
正在加载GUI桌面。
Here's the GUI desktop loading up.
到目前为止加载了很多。
A lot of loading so far.
没关系。
That's okay.
没有问题。
No problem.
等着就好
Just waiting.
Rob能会ssh进去
Rob might SSH in
关一些容器吗
and kill some containers.
用你在用的我的笔记本吗
From my laptop that you're on?
只是开玩笑
Just kidding.
好了
Here we go.
我们启动一个终端，然后好了
We spin up a terminal and boom.
对于这个介绍关卡，它会自动给我们一个flag。
For this intro challenge, it just automatically gives us a flag.
所有关卡都是基于flag的
Everything is flag based.
所有的分数都依赖你的flag
All the grades are relied in your flags.
复制一下这个flag
You copy this flag.
你复制它
You copy it.
哦,不。
Oh no.
Rob，发生什么事了?
Rob, what's happening?
好吧。
Okay.
总之，我们会在这里提交flag。
Anyways, we would submit the flag here and everything would be good.
我怕你必须ssh进入后台，才能使它工作
I'm terrified that you have to ssh in the background to make this work.
总之，没关系
Anyways, it's okay.
我不希望弹出某人的敏感信息
We're going to hope no one pops up sensitive notifications.
哦，看
Oh, look at that.
完美
Perfect.
我们回到桌面
Let's come back to the desktop
就是为了展示如何将里面的东西复制出来
just to show how to copy something out.
我都不知道怎么做
I don't even know how
我们在容器中复制这个
We copied this inside the container.
有一个小符号
There's this little character
如果你非常小心地点击这个符号
If you very carefully click on the character
点击这里
click here.
艹
fuck?
重申一下，这不是亚当·杜普说的
Again, that wasn't Adam Doupe saying that
尽管我…
even though I'm...
复制
Copy.
哦,不。
Oh no.
没关系。
That's okay.
然后，在这里
Then we go. Here it is.
把它从这个文本框中复制出来
Copy it out of this text box.
打开这个非常酷的界面
Bring up this really cool interface.
把这个粘贴进去
Paste this in.
点击提交
I'd hit submit.
就能得分了
It would give me the point
然后我可以进入下一关
and then I could go on to the next level.
它会来到下一关
It goes to the next level and we're all good to go.
好的
Okay.
这就是你解决这些挑战的方法
That's how you solve these challenges.
完成getting started
Go to the getting started
然后完成晚上8点发布的作业
and then go to the assignment that will launch at 8 PM.
本课程的所有交流都将在Discord上进行
All communication in this course will be on Discord.
如果你完成了前面的5个设置
If you go through and get the five chat boxes in the course setup
你会进入到正确的Discord频到
you will end up in the right Discord channels.
如果你不这样做，你就会挂科。
If you don't, you will fail the class.
评分，我提到过，分数都源于解决的题目。
Grading I mentioned all the grades depend on solving each challenge.
要通过这门课
To pass this class
你将会学会发现并利用XNU中的bug，真实的XNU
you will learn to find bugs in and exploit XNU, real XNU
我们尽可能搭建一个尽量真实的
on as real of a setting as we can get it
并且让解题难度呈线性
and still make it skillable for you guys to tackle.
还有一些额外的分数
There's also some extra credit.
通过在Discord上帮助他人，你可以获得高达5%的额外分数
You can get up to 5% extra credit by being helpful to others on Discord.
包括帮助pwn学院中其它班级的人
That also includes people in other pwn college classes.
你在Discord上乐于助人
You're helpful on Discord.
人们感谢你
People thank you.
有一个右击交互界面，可以用于感谢
There's a whole little right click app thank you sort of interface.
我们会记录下来并同步到5%的额外学分
We'll record that and synchronize extra credit up to 5%
用一个很神奇的对数公式
using a logarithmic formula that's very fancy.
但简单说，帮助别人，你会得到额外的学分。
But basically help people and you'll get extra credit.
然后每周你可以得到0.5%的学分
And then every week you can get half a percent
只需发布好的memes(迷因,表情包)
by posting good memes
需要得到meme频道某一个meme判官的认可
that one of the meme judges like in the meme channel.
请发一些好的meme
Please good memes.
应该不用我告诉你们
Shouldn't have to tell you all.
你们都是经验丰富的学生
You're all very experienced students.
不要发布粗制滥造的表情包。
Don't post low effort memes.
有一个“表情包监狱”。
There's also the meme jail.
如果你发布了一个粗制滥造的表情包
If you post a low effort meme
我可能会把你关进表情包监狱。
I might put you in meme jail.
在这学期剩下的时间里，你将被禁止发布表情包，除非有大赦
You will be barred from posting memes for the rest of the semester until there's a jailbreak.
总之
Anyways.
本课程的必备知识
Pre-requisite knowledge for this class.
这门课是ASU第二难的课
This class is the second hardest class at ASU.
目前最难的课显然是Rob的课
Hardest class at ASU so far demonstrably is Rob's class
今天他会接手
who will take over
狠狠“揍”你们一顿
and really pummel you guys today.
这可能是第二难的课了
This is probably the second hardest class.
也许它会登上王位，成为最难的课
Maybe it'll take the throne and become the hardest class.
希望你们上这门课前，知道pwn学院的所有知识
We expect you to come in knowing everything on pwn college.
这个单子基本上囊括了pwn学院的所有东西。
That list basically has everything on pwn college.
我们希望你们知道x86-64
We expect you to know x86-64
并且能逆向x86-64下的程序
and to be able to reverse engineer x86-64.
又跟丢我了
It lost track of me
好了
Come on. There we go.
希望你们知道如何编写shellcode
We expect you to know how to write shellcode
能编写阅读C代码
writing and reading C
能调试操作系统内核
debugging OS kernels,
所有这些之类的东西
all of this stuff that
我们会把这些幻灯片贴在PWN学院道场的课程上
we'll post these slides on the course in the pwn college dojo.
我们期待很多
We expect a lot.
你可以去学这些东西，比如，在pwn学院
You can learn a lot of this stuff. For example, on pwn college
你可以快速学一下
you can do it very rapidly.
我们没设置技能检查模块
We don't have a skill check module
我们相信你们
so we're going to trust your self-assessment
能挺过这门课的自我评估
that you're going to be able to survive this course.
我认为你们都能接受挑战
I think you can all rise to the challenge.
一些人可能会失败
Some of you might fail along the way
但我愿意接受这个代价
but that is a price I'm willing to pay.
好的
All right.
总之，不，我开玩笑的
Anyways, no, I'm just kidding.
这不是官方的亚当的想法
That also not an official Adam-ism.
好的
Okay.
我们来看看
Let's see.
本课程的所有内容都是实时构建的
Everything in this course we're building live as we deliver.
这是XNU上高级漏洞应用研究的第一版
This is the first iteration of the XNU version of advanced applied vulnerability research.
为什么这个东西总是跟丢我
Why is this thing insist on losing track of me?
所以课程可能有变动
This might change.
我们可能会发现
We might find that
其实我们无法支持
hey, we actually can't support
在pwn学院的ARM架构上运行真实的XNU
actually running the real XNU allocator in pwn college in ARM.
我们也许会切换到x64或别的
We might have to switch it to X64 Or something.
谁知道会发生什么
Who knows what will happen.
我们会尽力的
We'll do our best.
这类似pwn学院第一次授课
It'll be analogous to the very first run of a pwn college course ever.
在2018年的CSE466课程
The first run of 466 in 2018
那时尝试教内核模块
where there was an attempt to launch kernel modules
我把内核模块加载到了我用来讲课的笔记本上
where I was loading them onto my laptop that I was presenting from
然后和我有bug的内核模块交互
and then interacting with my buggy kernel module
结果毁了我的电脑和演讲
and killing my own laptop and killing the presentation.
所以任何事情都有可能发生
So anything could happen.
会很有趣的
It's going to be fun.
我们会学到很多关于XNU安全的知识
We're going to learn a lot about XNU security.
我们会成功的
We'll make it work.
好的
All right.
我，亚当·杜普，亚利桑那州立大学最酷的网络安全教授
Now that I, Adam Doupe, the coolest cyber security professor at ASU
记住这个会出现在考试中
remember this will be on a test.
你必须回答谁是ASU最酷的网络安全教授
You'll actually have to answer who's the coolest cyber security professor at ASU.
是谁?
Who is it?
twitch上的网友在吗
Is Twitch with us?
让我们来看看。
Let's see.
我们等一下twitch上的网友
We'll wait for Twitch.
你们会要回答这个问题
You'll have to answer that
不要忘记
Don't forget
我要走了，因为我吓到了大家
I'm going to bail now that I've scared everyone.
很不幸，我今天有事
I unfortunately have a thing today.
真是疯狂的一周
It's a crazy week.
请
Yes?
很快就好
Real quick.
在教学大纲上，你们还没有规定办公室时间。
So on the syllabus, you don't have office hours set yet.
你们有办公室时间吗?
Do you have office hours.
我不知道。
I don't know.
问下一周的我吧
Ask next week me.
我想是有的
I think so.
是的
Yes.
我得承认，伙计们，我不是亚当·杜普。
I have to admit, guys, I'm not really Adam Doupe.
亚当·杜普下周回来
Adam Doupe will be back next week.
但你可以告诉他，你更喜欢之前的亚当·杜普
But you can tell him that you like the previous Adam Doupe better.
通常这些课程有讲座和办公室时间
Usually these classes have the lecture and the office hours.
但是这堂课的课时是三个小时
But this lecture is three hours long lecture period.
所以这次我们有可能把它们结合起来
So it's possible that we'll combine it this time.
酷
Cool.
还有问题吗?
Any other questions?
谁是亚利桑那州立大学最酷的网络安全教授?
Who's the coolest cyber security professor at ASU?
好。
Good.
他们已经学到了一些东西
They learned something already.
完美
Perfect.
我会把你交给非常能干的罗伯·沃兹
I will leave you in the very capable hands of Rob Waz
他会帮助你们
who will teach you about the jump that you're about to take
从真善美的，你们喜欢的x86
from the good and right and proper x86 that you know and love as the one true architecture
进入到邪恶黑暗的ARM国度
and go into the dark evil realm of ARM
那里一切都是错的
where everything is wrong.
罗伯?
Rob?
好的
Okay.
看看接手成功了没
Let's see if we got it here.
看到了吗
See?
在跟着你吗
You following?
应该好了
I think we're there.
祝你好运
Good luck.
谢谢，Adam Doupe。
Thank you, Adam Doupe.
谁看过DEFCON上的“谁的ppt”
So who has seen whose slide is it anyway at DEFCON?
在这个活动中
It's an event they do
你会拿到一个随机的ppt
where you get a random slide deck
你需要在不知道会拿到什么ppt的情况下演讲
and you have to present not knowing what it is that you're gonna have.
现在基本就是这样的
That's basically what's gonna happen right now
刚刚Yan在台上的30分钟
because the 30 minutes that Yan talked
就是我看ppt的30分钟
was my 30 minutes I was gonna look at the slides.
所以我们就看看手里有什么，跟着它讲
So we're gonna see what we got and roll with it.
好吧？
Okay?
就是好奇
Just out of curiosity
谁有ARM64的使用经验?
who here has any experience with ARM64?
有人吗？
Anyone?
有人在挥手
We got some hand waving.
我相信你们
I'll take it.
如果我走错方向，请纠正我
Please correct me if I start stumbling in the wrong direction
因为这很有可能发生
because that is very likely to occur.
看看我们这里有什么
So let's see what we got here.
这是CPU的示意图。
This is a diagram of a CPU.
我们以前可能见过这张CPU图。
We've probably seen this diagram of a CPU before.
这个很流行
It's a pretty popular one.
它包含了很多部分
It has a lot of parts of stuff going on.
和你已知的非常相似
It's gonna be very similar to what you already know.
就cpu而言，汇编语言是唯一真正的编程语言
Assembly is the only true programming language as far as talking about CPUs
除非你学过CSE 466或CSE 598
except if you've taken CSE 466 or CSE 598
就是我教的软件利用课程
the software exploitation class that I teach
当时我们深入研究了微架构利用
where we kind of delve into micro architectural exploitation
了解到汇编也是个谎言
and you learn that assembly is also kind of a lie.
但就这门课的目标而言
but for the purposes of this class
我觉得我们不会讲得那么深
I don't think we're gonna go that deep.
所以汇编将是我们的基础真理
So assembly will be our ground truth.
在汇编中，我们都会做什么？
What kind of things do we do in assembly?
汇编是一种非常单纯的语言
Assembly is kind of a very simple language.
我们会做一些，如数据操控，比较
So we do things such as data manipulation, comparisons.
有控制流指令
We have control flow instructions
我们可以执行系统调用
and we can perform syscalls.
如果你了解x86，那这些你可能都看过了
If you know x86, you've probably seen all this.
汇编语言有寄存器的概念
Assembly language has this concept of registers.
这是存储数据的地方
This is where data is stored.
我们还可以和内存交互
We can also interact with memory.
内存中可以有正在执行的指令
Memory could be the instructions that are being executed
它们组成了程序
that it consist of the program.
我们可能会和栈交互
We could be interacting with the stack
或其它映射上的内存区域
or some other region of memory that happens to be mapped.
寄存器存在于CPU中
So registers exist on the CPU
它们是非常快速的临时数据存储区
and they're very fast temporary stores of data.
寄存器是一种通用存储
Registers serve as kind of a general purpose storage.
大多数寄存器都没有指定的含义
Most registers, they don't have an assigned meaning.
这个概念可以一直追溯到我们拥有的第一种cpu 8085
This concept goes all the way back to the very first kind of CPUs where we had the 8085.
这些寄存器很小
These registers were very small
在历代Intel的CPU中，延续了一套命名规范
and we'll notice kind of a consistent naming mechanism in the Intel kind of history of CPUs.
原来我们有a c d e
Where originally we had a,c,d,e
然后来到8086架构。
then we went to the 8086 architecture.
这些寄存器稍微大一点
These registers were a little bit bigger.
变成了ax cx dx bx。
All of a sudden it's ax,cx,dx,bx.
我们到了x86
We got to x86
这是一个32位的架构
which is a 32-bit architecture.
这里
This is where
其中一些寄存器你们现在可能比较熟悉了
some of these registers may be something that you are a bit more familiar with now.
我们有EAX ECX EDX。
We had EAX, ECX, EDX.
然后我们看到ESP和EBP。
And then we see ESP and EBP.
这些不是通用寄存器。
These are not general purpose registers.
有人知道ESP或EBP是什么吗?
Does anyone know what ESP or EBP is by chance?
直接告诉我吧
Just hit me.
我喜欢互动
I like interaction.
有什么回答？
What do we got?
栈指针和基指针。
Stack pointer and base pointer.
这就是这个缩写的意思
That is in fact what the acronym stands for.
在英特尔无限的智慧中
In Intel's infinite wisdom
EBP在技术上是一个栈帧指针
EBP is technically a frame pointer
我觉得这有点搞笑
which I think is kind of funny.
但，没错，从缩写来看，这是正确的。
But yes, based upon the acronym, that is correct.
然后到了AMD64
then we get to AMD64
Yan很爱这个架构
which is the architecture that Yan truly loves
并且绝大多数pwn学院的设备都是这个
and is definitely what the vast majority of pwn college has been.
这里我们能看到64位的寄存器，RAX,RCX,RDX等等
That's where we see the 64-bit versions of these registers, RAX, RCX, RDX, etc.
现在我们看到的是最现代的计算机了
And now we are kind of at what most modern computing is.
这门课
Now for this class
正如Yan提到的
as Yan mentioned
我们将尝试在ARM上做所有的事情
we're going to try and do everything on ARM
ARM是一个非常不同的指令集
And ARM is a very different instruction set.
我们的通用寄存器是X0 X1 X2 X3。
And so our general purpose registers are X0, X1, X2, X3.
就是X 加上一个数字
They're just X and a number.
它们都是通用寄存器
They're all just general purpose registers.
这里有个问题
Now there is kind of a gotcha there
如果ppt上有，我们会看到
that we'll see if it's on the slides.
我们拭目以待
We'll find out.
值得注意的是
It is worth noting that
在AMD64上，你习惯使用的EIP或RIP
on AMD64 where you were used to having EIP or RIP
就是你的指令指针
which is your instruction pointer.
在ARM上，你实际上不能
On ARM you actually can't directly interact with RIP
直接与RIP等同的指令指针交互
the equivalent for the instruction pointer.
酷
Cool.
在AMD64中，如你可能熟悉的
In AMD64, as you're probably familiar
RAX是64位寄存器
RAX is the 64-bit register
你可以用EAX访问RAX中的一部分
You can access a subsection of that with EAX
然后是AX的那一小部分
and then a smaller subsection with AX
然后是AL的那一小部分。
and then a smaller subsection with AL.
你可以访问部分寄存器
You can address partial registers.
ARM也有类似的情况
There's a similar phenomenon here with ARM.
不同的是，我们现在有X
The difference here is we have XN
它是64位寄存器
which is going to be your 64-bit register
然后是W，这是一个32位寄存器。
and then we have WN, which is a 32-bit register.
这里只有两种尺寸
So we just have two sizes here.
ARM是一个简化的指令集
ARM is a reduced instruction set
所以它确实有一些我们可能不熟悉的东西
so it does have some things that we probably aren't familiar with
或者说，我们不能很好地映射到AMD64的东西
or that we can't really map well to AMD64.
其中之一就是零寄存器的概念
One of these things is the concept of a zero register.
这是一个总是为零的寄存器
This is a register that just always has zero.
每次从中取值
Anytime we move something from it
你都会得到0
you're going to get zero
往它里面写，等同于nop
writing to it is essentially a nop
但它确实存在
but it exists.
ARM有四个栈指针
ARM has four stack pointers
我也不清楚
which I didn't know
因为我没有接触过ARM的不同权限级别
because I haven't interacted with different privilege levels on ARM
这很令人期待
so that will be something exciting to see.
ARM还有一个链接寄存器和栈帧指针。
ARM also has a link register and frame pointer.
链接寄存器是
The link register is
在AMD64中
So in AMD64
当您执行呼叫时
when you perform a call
你会将要保存的返回地址压到栈上
you push the saved return address onto the stack.
ARM上的链接寄存器
The link register on ARM
就放着要保存的返回地址
holds that saved return address
在call的等效指令被执行时
when the equivalent instruction is executed.
希望这在后面的幻灯片中会提到
Hopefully, that's mentioned a bit more later in the slides.
如果没有，我们将尝试进行现场演示，看看会发生什么
If not, we'll try and live demo it and see what happens.
我不关心V寄存器。
I don't care about V registers.
没有人想处理SIMD
Nobody wants to deal with SIMD.
ARM指令是如何工作的?
How do ARM instructions work?
在x86中，通常是这样的模式，操作码 目标，源
so in x86, we typically have this pattern of opcode destination, source.
在ARM中，是操作码，操作数，操作数，操作数，操作数，操作数。
With ARM, we have opcode, operand, operand, operand, operand, operand.
你有多个操作数
You have a various number of operands.
这里，我们看到mov遵循类似的模式
Here we see move follows that similar pattern.
我们可以 mov x0, x2
We could have move x0, x2
还可 add x0, x0, 接着一个#1
add, x0, x0, and then hash 1.
实际上有
There actually is
以后会找找看，但我相信
we'll find out, but I believe
2个操作数版本的add
a two operand version of add.
3个操作数版本的add，指定了目标的位置
The three version operand of add is specifying where the destination is.
add x0,x0, #1 等价于 add x0, #1
Add x0, x0, 1 is the equivalent to add x0, 1.
但如果想用2个寄存器的值相加，结果放到第三个寄存器
but If for some reason we wanted to add two registers and store it in a third register
我们就可以通过3个操作数实现
we have the ability to do that by specifying three operands.
类似地，有一些你们之前见过的东西
Similarly, we have things that you've seen before
比如比较和分支
things like compare and then branch.
这里的分支，B代表分支
Now, branch here, B for branch is
相当于x86的jmp跳转指令
the equivalent of a x86 jump instruction.
偷看一下
Sneak a peek.
ppt会有这些吗
Does he go there?
我不知道。
I don't know.
我先说了
I'm going to hit it earlier.
jmp对应分支b
Jump is B for branch.
call，就是我说的“嘿，有这个链接寄存器”
Call, which is where I mentioned, hey, this link register exists.
call，在ARM上对应 BL
Call, the equivalent on arm, is BL
它是分支并链接的缩写
which is an acronym for branch and link.
也就是说
That is saying
嘿，我们要跳到某个地方
hey, we're going to jump somewhere
但我们也会在链接寄存器里放一个值
but we're also going to put a value in that link register
这样我们就能返回回来
so that we have somewhere to return to.
怎么了
Yes?
PC到底是什么?
What exactly is the PC?
我在哪儿
Where am I?
什么是……
What is the...
什么是链接寄存器?
What is the link register?
哦,PC吗?
Oh, PC?
PC，我想是程序计数器的缩写
PC So that is, I believe the acronym there is program counter
这是指令指针的另一种说法
which is just another term for the instruction pointer.
所以，它是ARM上对应的RIP吗
So basically i mean the arm equivalent of RIP.
PC相当于RIP吗
PC is the arm equivalent of RIP.
你甚至可以在x86上的GDB中用到PC
I believe you can even use PC in GDB on x86.
它是指令指针的通称
It's a generic term for the instruction pointer.
我们能看到，链接寄存器会在BL执行时用到
And we see here that this link register is used on BL
BL相当于x86上的call
which is the equivalent of the x86 call.
当ret时
And then when we ret
实际发生的是
what's really happening is
我们将RIP改成LR中存的值
we are setting RIP to whatever is stored in LR.
很酷吧
Cool?
为什么要有操作数，操作数，操作数，操作数?
Why do we have operand, operand, operand, operand?
我不知道
I don't know.
我不知道为什么
I don't know why.
但ARM的优点之一是，每条指令的大小都是32位
But one of the nice things about ARM is that every instruction is 32 bits in size.
一旦你习惯了，这其实是一件很酷的事情
And this is something that's actually kind of cool once you get used to it
因为你可以更容易地推理和解释指令
because you can reason and interpret instructions a lot easier.
例如，在x86上，大多数push指令的长度只有两个字节
So on x86, for instance, most push instructions are only two bytes in length.
但是如果你想mov一个32位的常量
But if you wanted to move a 32-bit constant
那将是32位加上一个数
that's going to be 32 bits plus something else.
因此，单个汇编指令的长度在x86上是不同的
So the length of an individual assembly instruction will vary on x86.
但在ARM上，每条指令都是32位的固定长度。
But on ARM, every instruction is a fixed length of 32 bits.
这听起来真的很酷
Now that sounds really cool.
但你仔细思考一下会发现
But then when you start thinking about it
AMD64有这些可变长度指令是有原因的
there's a reason that AMD64 has these variable length instructions.
AMD64中，如果我想mov一个32位常量
I said if I have AMD64 and I want to move a 32-bit constant
这个32位常量必须在指令中
well, that 32-bit constant has to be in the instruction.
如果我的指令长度限制在32位
If my instructions are limited to 32 bits in length
那我该如何mov一个32位常量呢
how do I move a 32-bit constant?
事实证明，你不能
Turns out you can't.
这是个问题
That's a problem
因为我要mov的数字大于
because the number I want to move is larger
指令长度的限制
than my limitation on the instruction length.
正因为如此
And because of that
ARM64会有一些有趣的机制
ARM64 has some interesting mechanics
希望在后面的幻灯片中会讲到
that hopefully are included in the later slides.
ARM64和AMD64之间有一种弱关联性
So here we have kind of a loose equivalency between ARM64 and AMD64 here.
如果我们要
So if we're going to
例如，mov rax, rbx
for instance, mov rbx into rax
等价的指令是mov x0, x1
the equivalent instruction is going to be mov x0, x1.
如果我们想解引用一个内存地址
If we want to dereference a memory address
我们遵守一个类似我们已知的模式
we follow a similar pattern to kind of what we've already seen.
我们在AMD64上有这个mov
We have that move on AMD64.
在amd64上是mov rax 跟着 [ RBP+4 ]
We have that move RAX and then the brackets RBX plus 4.
在ARM上等价的是, mov x0,
The equivalent on ARM is we move x0,
也有方括号
We still have the brackets.
但是注意这个常数
But note that the constant
任何时候我引用一个常量，它都以 #符号开始
anytime I'm referencing a constant, it starts with that hash symbol.
所以模式和之前的基本一样
So we still have that same general kind of pattern that you've seen.
这里的add，我们已经讨论过了。
over here, add, we've talked about that.
mul
mul.
那么你认为mul x5, x6, x7是什么效果
So what do you think mul x5, x6, x7 does?
根据我说过的
Just based on what I've already said.
我们有三个操作码
We got three opcodes.
都有什么回答
What do we got?
好的
Okay.
Twitch上的回答是
So the statement for Twitch is
我们取x6和x7的值
we're going to take x6 and x7
把它们相乘
we're going to multiply them
把结果放入x5
and we're going to put the result in x5.
听起来没毛病
Sounds good to me
我们有三个操作码
We got three opcodes.
好了，这已经说得通了
All right, this makes sense already
我还什么都没做
and I haven't really done anything.
这很好
This is good.
如果能想得通，说明应该是跟上了
If you made that logical leap, you might be in the right room.
好的，add x0, x0, #0x1
Okay, add x0, x0, hash x1.
有人回答吗
Any takers?
这是在做什么？
What are we doing?
来吧
Come on.
那边的同学
You right there.
这是在做什么？
What are we doing?
在将x0的值加1，然后把结果放到x0
You're adding one to x0 and storing the result into x0.
好的，漂亮
All right, that's beautiful.
所以答案是
So the answer is
我们取x0中的值
we're taking the value in x0
加上常数1
adding the constant one to it
把结果存储在x0中
and storing it in x0.
现在我们有一些不同的缩略词
Now we have a few kind of acronyms that are a little bit different
但它们很容易学会。
but they're pretty easy to pick up.
这里我看到了
So right here I see
ldr x0然后解引用x1
ldr x0 and then we are kind of dereferencing x1.
LDR是加载寄存器的缩写。
ldr is a shorthand acronym here for load register.
我们要从内存中加载一些东西
So we're going to load something from memory
我们要把它存到这个寄存器里
we're going to store it in the register
我们从x0加载到
we are loading from x0
抱歉，是从x1中的内存地址处加载
I'm sorry, loading from the memory address defined in x1
存储到x0寄存器
we are storing it in the register x0.
根据刚刚说的，你认为str是什么?
Now what do you think str is based on what I just said?
哦，有人说是存储寄存器
Oh, we got store register.
我们做得很好，伙计们。
We are doing good, guys.
我们已经上手了
We're on a hot, you know, we're on it
小菜一碟
just crushing it.
好的，这个有点难
All right, now this one's a trick.
STP是什么?
What's STP?
你们觉得呢?
What do you think?
好的，有人说 存储 指针
Okay, we got store pointer.
我不知道的话，也会这样猜
That would make, I would guess that if I didn't know better.
我听到了不一样的回答
What was, I heard something else.
说的好像是栈指针
Something about stack pointer.
好的，字母上说得通
Okay, those letters make sense.
我能接受
I'd take that.
还有一个回答
We got one more.
好吧，这个有点怪
Okay, now that is a weird thing to say.
Twitch上的回答
For Twitch here.
好，好，好
Yeah, yeah, yeah, all right.
直觉告诉我，你之前接触过ARM
Something tells me you've messed around with ARM before.
直播间上说的是，STP是存储对的缩写
So the statement here for the stream is STP is an acronym for store pair.
这是我们在AMD64上完全没有的东西
This is something that we don't have, in equivalent really, at all on AMD64.
所以我们在存储
And so we're storing
我们取这一对寄存器
so we're taking the pair of registers
X1和x2
x1 and x2
它们的尺寸有多大?
which are how big in size?
听到了一些回答
I heard a few things.
有哪些回答？
What do we got?
有一个说的是32位
All right, so one of the statements was 32 bits.
另一个说的是64位
The other one was 64 bits.
x寄存器是64位的
So the x registers are 64 bits.
w寄存器在访问低32位
The w registers are accessing the lower 32 bits.
当我们stp x1 x2
So when we have store pair x1, x2
我们实际上存储了两个64位寄存器
we are actually storing two 64 bit registers
到x0中定义的内存地址
to the memory location that is defined in x0.
所以这一条指令，移动了128位数据
So this is one instruction that is moving 128 bits.
在一条指令中，将两个寄存器的数据放入内存
We're putting two registers worth of data to memory in one instruction.
所以这肯定有点奇怪
So things definitely get a little bit weird.
根据下一张幻灯片的内容，还能变得更怪
And they can get weirder depending on what's in the next slide.
好吧，也没那么奇怪
Okay, well that isn't that weird.
拜托，我们比这强
Come on, we can do better than that.
在这里能看到，可以访问寄存器中的部分数据
Here we see that you can access smaller amounts of data in a register.
在AMD64中也有同样的现象
We have the same phenomenon here in AMD64.
例如，我们可以，加载一个字节，半个字，一个字
So we can, for instance, load an individual byte, a half word, a word.
我不认为这特别有趣
I don't think that's particularly interesting.
但你能看到，我们是如何添加后缀，来完成这个的
But you see how we can suffix these instructions to pull that off.
啊哦，我不知道BFI是什么
Uh oh, I don't know what BFI is.
哦，幻灯片有说明
Oh, the slide says it.
它说，指令可以移动或操纵bit，从一个寄存器，到另一个寄存器
It says, "Instructions can move and manipulate bits from one register to another"
位 域 插入
A bit field insert
好吧，那好吧。
Okay, all right, then.
我们看看这里有什么
Let's see what we got here.
bfi x1, x0， #9， #6。
BFI X1, X0, #9, #6.
我有四个操作数
So I've got four operands.
我们要把低六位移到X1中
We're going to move the lower six bits into X1.
其中x1的第9位，是x0的最低位
Where bit nine in X1 is the lowest
这是啥？
what?
有人帮我翻译一下吗?
And anyone translate this for me?
你有个猜测吗
We got a guess?
没有
We don't got a guess.
当我们遇到未知的事物，要怎样？
So what happens if we don't know something?
你的总体策略是什么?
What's your general strategy?
如果你在网络安全领域走了这么远，你可能不会...
If you've made it this far in cybersecurity, you're probably not...
身处未知对你来说并不陌生
Being in the unknown is not foreign to you.
我们该怎么办?
What should we do?
我们正在分析幻灯片
We're parsing the slide.
栈溢出？
Stack overflow.
好的，这很好。
Okay, that's pretty good.
这很好。
That's pretty good.
如果是个别的话题，我会读man手册
If this were a different topic, I would have said read the man page.
对吧?
Right?
我们这里没有man手册
We don't have man pages here
但幻灯片底部藏了些东西
but one of the things that is hiding at the bottom of these slides
其中之一是ARM文档
is the ARM documentation
曾经在pwn学院的道场有链接
which used to be linked in the pwn College Dojo and
后来ARM换了网页地址
then ARM changed the web address.
所以现在它不在这里了
So now it doesn't go here.
它实际上是非常详实可靠的文档
It's actually very solid documentation.
看看我们能不能找到答案
Let's see if I can find the right one.
我们看一下这里
And we can take a look here.
我在找什么
What am I looking for?
BFI吗?
BFI?
位域插入，这是BFM的别名
Bitfield insert, which apparently is an alias for BFM.
ppt上有这个吗
Did he have that there?
会讲到bfm吗
Did he get us BFM?
不会
No.
看到了吗?
See?
这告诉我们它是个别名
I'm showing us this is alias, all right?
文档就是真理
Documentation is truth.
BFM。
BFM.
有什么描述
What do we got here?
哦，现在它说，它总是通过别名访问。
Oh, now it just says it's always accessed by its alias.
那为什么还要有实际的BFM指令呢
Then why have the real instruction?
好吧
Okay.
它是拷贝了寄存器的一个子集
So it's copying a subset of the register from 8 bit
我信了
I'll take it.
指令可视化
Instruction visualization.
哦，我应该直接看下一张幻灯片
Oh, I should have just gone to the next slide.
我们一起学习一下
Let's learn together here.
都讲了啥
What do we got?
BFI X1 X0 #9 #6。
So I got BFI X1, X0, #9, #6.
这里的9在哪里
Where does 9 fit in here?
6在哪里
Where does 6 fit in here?
好吧。
Okay.
BFI。
BFI.
哦，这里改成w了
Oh, he's going for a W now
和上一张ppt是不同的寄存器
so a different register.
9,6。
9, 6.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
好的
All right.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
好的
All right.
看明白了
These numbers kind of make sense.
我们从右边的寄存器取数据
So we are grabbing from this first register
然后放到一个偏移处，这里的9
and we are moving it into an offset
然后是我们要复制的长度，这里的6
and then a length into it that we're copying.
ARM侠，你知道吗?
Did ARM man, did you know it?
你也不知道
You didn't know it either.
我感觉好点了
I feel a little bit better.
还有什么
What do we got here?
UBFX，这是干嘛的
UB, what are you doing here?
这是什么把戏?
What is this shenanigans?
UBFX
从X1的第18最低位，移动7位，到X0的最低位。
moves 7 bits in X1 starting from the 18th lowest bit to the lowest bit in X0.
这在功能上是一样的，不是吗?
That's like functionally the same thing, isn't it?
是的，因为我们走到第18位
Yes, because we're going 18 deep.
取7位
We're grabbing 7
然后把它放到这个寄存器的开头
and we're throwing it here at the beginning.
它们是相反的操作
So they're inverse operations.
第一个指令
In the first one here
我们在源寄存器的开头取数据
we are grabbing from the beginning of the source
然后我们定义目标寄存器的偏移量。
and then we're defining the offset at the destination.
然后我们再看看UBFX
Then here we look at UBFX
我们定义源寄存器的偏移量
we are setting the offset in the source
然后把它放到目标寄存器的开头
and then putting it at the beginning of the destination.
我们理清了
We got there.
我相信
I'll take it.
为什么这个取到的是0
Why does this thing grab 0
最下面这个示例
this last one here?
BFI W1 wzr 3 4
We got BFI W1 WZR 3 4.
这些0是从哪里来的?
Where do these zeros come from?
这是个刁钻的问题。
It's a trick question.
其实不是
Not really.
WZR是一个零寄存器
WZR is a zero register.
零寄存器
Zero register.
是的
Yeah.
WZR，回到之前的幻灯片，是一个零寄存器。
So WZR, calling back to the earlier slides, is a zero register.
所以我们是从零寄存器的开头复制一些东西
So we are copying something from the beginning of the zero register
它都是0
which is all zeros.
我们定义了偏移量
We're defining the offset
这能让我们在目标寄存器中将一定数量的位归零
which allows us to zero a certain number of bits in our destination register.
ARM64上没有push或pop指令
So there are no push or pop instructions on ARM64.
这太糟糕了。
That kind of sucks.
我们现实一点
Let's be real here.
相反，我们有前索引和后索引的概念
Instead, we have this concept of pre-indexing and post-indexing.
我们有这样一个概念，在访问一个值时
We have this concept of accessing a value
同时对它进行递增或递减。
while simultaneously incrementing it or decrementing it.
并且我们可以在访问前递增或递减
And we can increment or decrement it before the access
或者在访问后递增或递减
or increment or decrement it after the access
希望这里我们有展示
which is hopefully what we have showing here.
我们确实有
We do have it.
我得查一下我的笔记，以确保我说对了
I have to consult my handy notes here to make sure I get this right
我不想在直播上说错
because I don't want to say it wrong on stream.
这里有str
So here we have store register.
将x4寄存器中的值
We're going to store the value that is in register X4
存储到栈指针-8字节的位置
to the stack pointer minus eight bytes.
但这个感叹号是干什么用的呢?
But what is this exclamation point doing?
Twitch直播间里说
So the comment from Twitch is
会先做减法
we're going to first perform this subtraction.
这是前索引
This is a pre-index.
所以我们会保存到栈指针-8的位置
So we are storing this at the stack pointer minus eight
因为有一个感叹号
because we have this exclamation point.
这里是stp
Here we have store pair.
所以我们存储16字节
So we are storing 16 bytes.
有感叹号
We have the exclamation point.
所以这是前索引
So this is a pre-index.
我们将这对寄存器，存储到栈指针减去
We are storing this pair at the stack pointer minus
我不会算
I can't math
128位
128 bits.
16个字节
16 bytes.
这相当于在一条指令中执行两次push
So it's the equivalent of doing two pushes in one instruction.
有点像AMD64
Kind of pulling over from AMD64.
这个没有感叹号
This one right here does not have the exclamation point.
另一个不同的语法
We have a different syntax.
我们加载这对X0, X1
So we have load pair X0, X1.
我们正在访问栈指针
We're accessing the stack pointer.
然后有一个逗号和一个常数
And then we have a comma and a constant.
这是后索引
This is a post-index.
我们从栈指针指向的内存中取出数据
So we are pulling this from the stack pointer
然后进行加法运算
and then performing the addition.
这相当于做了两次pop
It's the equivalent of doing two pops
对应这里的两条指令
which is what we have over here.
类似地，这也是一个后索引
Similarly, this is a post-index.
我们先获取栈指针指向内存的值
So we're going to grab the value of the stack pointer
扔进X4
throw it in X4
然后栈指针+8
and then add to the stack pointer
所以这相当于一次pop
so it's the equivalent of a single pop.
我们必须注意这个后索引、前索引的记号
But we have to be aware of this post-index, pre-index notation.
分支
Branching.
老实说，我觉得ARM上的分支比AMD64上的好理解
Branching, honestly, I think is kind of easier to understand on ARM than AMD64.
因为B代表分支
Because we just have B for branch
然后是条件式后缀
and then you have this conditional kind of suffix.
所以指令是b.接着你看到的这些
So it's B dot and then what are you looking at?
我不关心这个
I don't care about that.
条件选择：csel
Conditional select.
ARM侠，你能帮帮我吗
Arm man, you got me?
不行？
No?
没关系
It's all right.
我们可以直接去查文档
We can just go to the documentation, man.
好吧
Okay, yeah.
如果我们分析一下幻灯片的逻辑
If we actually just parse the logic of the slides
我们可能会到达那里
we might get there.
这张幻灯片的逻辑是
So the logic of the slides here says
我们根据条件将Xd设为Xn或Xm
that we are setting Xd to either Xn or Xm based upon condition.
亚当在这上面研究的很深
Adam went deep into ARM on this one, man.
系统调用
Syscalls.
这里没有syscall指令
We don't have a syscall instruction.
我们有svc
We have a service instruction.
其余的
The rest of them
我不知道，伙计。
I don't know, man.
亚当会帮助你们
Adam's going to have to save you there.
系统调用号
The syscall number
在amd64上是在x8寄存器中（口误）
which traditionally on AMD64 is going to be an x8
在AMD64上是在rax
on AMD64 would be an rax.
ARM中，它将会在x8
On ARM is going to be an x8.
AMD64上syscall的调用约定
A calling convention for the syscall on AMD64
你已经习惯了rdi rsi rdx等等，
you're used to rdi, rsi, rdx, blah, blah,
ARM上它变得更简单
ARM actually kind of makes it kind of easy.
我们就从0开始数
We just start counting from zero up.
这些是你的参数
Those are your arguments.
在这之后，我记得是x7之后，就放在栈上了
After this, I believe after x7, they end up on the stack.
所以我们并没有填满所有的通用寄存器
So we don't actually fill every general purpose register.
哦，你知道吗
Oh, what do you know?
我们讲过这个了
We got there.
调用约定
So calling conventions.
如我提到的，函数调用指令是bl，分支并链接
As I mentioned, calling function is bl for branch and link.
返回地址，没放到栈，而是放到链接寄存器中
The return address, instead of being pushed to the stack, is stored in this link register.
如果链接寄存器中已经有值了
If you have something in the link register
然后你再次分支
and you branch again
那原来的值会放到栈上
it does end up on the stack
先前函数帧的返回地址
the prior return address from the earlier function frames.
调用约定，被调保存的
Calling conventions, callee-saved.
好的
That's fine.
酷
Cool.
到结尾了吗
Did I make it to the end?
我们到结尾了
We made it to the end.
上课多长时间了
How long since class go?
有一件事
One of the things I don't think
我要说一下
I'm just going to throw it out there.
这门课没有课本
There is no textbook for the class
但我要说
but I will say that this book
有时会参考到这本书
is loosely going to be kind of referred to
或者用做这门课的参考
or used as a reference for how the class works.
不是必需的
Not required.
这本书很难买到
It is a hard book to acquire.
你不能像普通书那样在亚马逊上下单。
You can't just like order it on Amazon as like a normal bookstore thing.
只有一个卖家，那就是作者。
There's like one seller and it's the author.
这本书本身已经过时好几年了
The book itself is several years out of date.
它有几个版本
There's several versions.
有一个叫Star操作系统
So there's the Star OS
还有一个老一点的名字稍微不同
and then there's slightly different name that's an older version.
他们俩都够老
Both of them are old enough to where
以至于，描述的很多实现细节，比如Mac OS的
a lot of the implementation details that are described there as far as Mac OS
都不一定是准确的
aren't necessarily accurate.
但总的思路是准确的
But the general feel of it
如果你解析它，然后尝试一些东西
if you parse it and then just try stuff
你能在尝试的过程弄清楚
you can figure stuff out as you go.
获取相关信息其实非常困难
Getting that information is actually very hard.
这些机制工作原理的公开信息并不多
There's not a lot of public information on how those mechanisms work.
下一个问题是
The next question is
Yan在讲的时候，我安装的东西成了吗
did what I was installing work while Yan was lecturing?
赌一下
Here's our big gamble.
进入示例前，有人有问题吗
Does anyone have any questions for me before I just bomb a demo?
该死
Damn.
是啊，我希望你们能救救我
Yeah, I was hoping you guys would save me.
理论上讲
In theory here
我弄了一个在ARM上运行的docker环境
what I have is a Docker environment that's running on ARM
这意味着我们应该能够使用一些熟悉的Pwntools
which means we should be able to use some familiar PwnTools things
来编译并运行一些ARM汇编
to kind of just compile and run some ARM assembly.
from pwn import *
from pwn import star.
哦，我安装了GDB。
Oh, I did install GDB.
我们来看看是否可行。
So let's see if that works.
哦,不。
Oh no.
GDB不会起作用
I know GDB doesn't work.
这个演示吹了
The demo is ruined.
不,不。
No, no.
准确的说是在Mac上
Specifically on a Mac
如果你是在mac上通过Rosetta
if you're using Rosetta on a Mac
来使用GDB，那么你必须执行一些特殊的操作
to use GDB there's some special magic you have to do.
我没做这些操作
And I did not do such magic.
我不记得这些操作了
I don't remember the magic.
好的，伙计们。
All right guys.
所以，我想，这就是我能给你的全部了
So that is, I suppose, all I can hit you with.
第一个任务，正如Yan提到的
One of the first assignments, as Yan mentioned
会在8点发布
is live at 8 o'clock
不过说实话，你可以在这里访问
although honestly you can access it right here
不在你的dojo中
not under your dojos.
但据我所知
But as far as I'm aware
这与社区ARM dojo上的题目完全相同
it's the exact same challenges that are on the community ARM dojo.
它会做些特别的限制，让你使用这些奇怪的指令
It does specifically try and make you utilize some of these odd instructions.
这是为了教育
It is meant to be educational.
他不像？？
It's not like the giant, hey, get pumped.
如果我们用dojo代替我失败的GDB演示
And so if we use the dojo instead of my amazing GDB demo that failed
我用SSH连接到它
I'm going to use SSH to connect to it.
希望道场没有忙到着火
Hopefully the dojo is not on fire.
我们会知道的
We'll find out.
漂亮
Beautiful.
这些挑战一开始很简单
So these challenges start off very simple.
只是简单的，嘿，让我们设置一个寄存器。
It's just, hey, let's set a register.
希望你们知道如何操作
Hopefully you knew that.
我们要mov X1 然后跟着一个#开头的常量
We're going to move X1 and then a constant start with the hash.
等到后面的题目
As you get to the later challenges
它会开始对你施加限制
it's going to start putting restrictions on you
比如，你只能使用特定的指令
where you can only use specific instructions
或者我们要限制指令的数量
or we're going to limit the number of instructions.
这时候，你就要使用到这些了
And so now you're going to have to start using some of these
例如，stp，ldp。
for instance, storing pairs, loading pairs.
你会用到后索引，前索引
You're going to have to deal with that post index, pre index
来优化你的汇编代码
to optimize your assembly
这样原来你要用，比如10条指令，写的东西
so that something that you could write in say 10 instructions
现在只需要4条了
you're now going to have to do in like four.
一般来说，ARM的指令数量很少
In general, ARM has a small number of instructions
但是一条指令可以做很多事情
but a single instruction will do a lot of things
这取决于你如何构建它
depending upon how you structure it
这让它变得很酷
which makes it kind of cool.
这个道场的目的是希望让你利用上一些这样的概念
This dojo is designed to hopefully make you utilize some of those concepts.
到此，我没有要讲的了
With that, I got nothing.
如果你们没什么问题，我们就要结束了
If you got nothing, we're going to call it.
我看看twich，看看有没有提问
I'll check Twitch and see if my favorite troll has hit me.
我想他们在睡觉
I think they're sleeping.
是的，在睡觉。
Yeah, the troll is sleeping.
有人在Twitch上说
Somebody says on Twitch
需要学习pwn学院上的哪条学习路线
what is the path on pwn College that I need to follow
才能达到这门课的要求
to get the requirements for this course, CSE598?
这是一个很普遍的问题
That's a fair general question.
pwn学院作为一个网站是对所有人开放的
So pwn College as a site in general is open to everyone.
如果我们到这里的dojos
If we go to dojos here
你可以看到橙，黄，绿，蓝的进度。
you see this progression of orange, yellow, green, blue.
这门课还不在这些进度中
This course is not in anywhere currently in this progression
但它相当于这个蓝带的水平
but it would be equivalent to this blue belt level
就期望而言
as far as the expectations.
如果你想达到这门课预期的所需知识
so If you wanted to have the requisite acknowledged
你需要学习橙、黄和绿带
you would want to go through orange, yellow, and green
解释一下
for a little bit of perspective.
这大约相当于ASU两个学期的300和400级的大学课程
That's roughly two semesters worth of university education at the 300 and 400 level here at ASU
至于大家通常预计的所需知识
as far as what the general expectations going in are.
就是说，橙带的所需知识
So to start the orange belt
大致是你要有几年常规计算机科学的知识储备
it's kind of assuming you have a couple years of general computer science under your belt.
如果Twitch上没有别的问题的话
If there's nothing else on Twitch
我估计没了
which I don't believe there is
我们就讲到这里
we're going to wrap up there.
很感谢大家的参与
I appreciate everyone hanging out.
下周会是真正的亚当来讲
Next week should be the real Adam.